Emily: Saj and Rebecca are both doctors
and they’ve been together for nine years. She’s a vegan, he’s not.
Rebecca: When I see anyone eat meat, but in particular Saj,
it’s a thing that’s quite hard to describe to people who aren’t vegan.
It’s not just nauseating and kind of a little bit gross,
it’s also something, kind of, profoundly hurtful,
so it’s even worse watching someone that you love doing that
and I think that’s where the tolerance has to come from.
Saj: My favourite meaty meal is a chicken teriyaki.
Like, that’s the thing that I really hanker for.
So, if I’m finishing work, I walk past this Japanese restaurant
and they’ve got just this most amazing chicken teriyaki.
Emily: Do you tell Rebecca about it when you get home?
Saj: Um, no I – I usually don’t. Just depends on how brave I’m feeling.
Emily: I went to meet Saj and Rebecca at their flat in south-east London.
Occasionally, Saj smuggles in some milk chocolate desserts,
but, other than that, this is a meat- and dairy-free zone.
Rebecca: Tonight is, well, it’s Friday, so it’s fish and chip night.
So, we’re having a vegan version with some vegan scampi.
Emily: And can I see this fake scampi that you’re going to cook?
So, rehydrated textured soy and wheat protein.
Saj, when you look at this, does your heart fill with joy?
Would you prefer real scampi bites?
Saj: Yeah, I really like scampi, but my heart doesn’t go,
‘Oh God, give me the real stuff!’
I’ll just be like, right, let’s try it, bring it on.
Emily: Come on, would you not prefer some sausages?
Saj: Um, ooh, yeah, if they’re going.
But if I’m eating with Beck I always think that…
it’s, like, one of my rules that we should eat together
and we should always have the same meal.
Emily: At first, Rebecca would eat a little bit of fish
and chicken when she was with Saj,
even occasionally cooking him sausages.
But she never felt entirely comfortable with it
and eventually stopped eating meat altogether.
Then, two and a half years ago, she became vegan,
motivated by her strong feelings about animal welfare and the environment.
She says over time it’s become increasingly hard to watch Saj eat meat.
Rebecca: I know that he eats meat,
but because he doesn’t do it very often in front of me I don’t have to deal with it,
so I can kind of just pretend it’s not happening.
Emily: Some people listening might be thinking,
‘How can you actually be in a relationship with someone
when you find a part of their life morally repugnant?’
Rebecca: I think because we’ve been together so long,
and Saj is the most important person in my life
and he’s made huge efforts to not eat a lot of meat and dairy and he is, kind of,
shifting more towards my way of thinking, it makes it a little bit more tolerable.
Emily: When did you last see Saj eat meat?
Rebecca: The weekend before last.
Emily: And where were you?
Rebecca: Er, we went to visit my parents.
And it’s like the worst situation that he could have done it in as well,
’cause I’ve been telling my mum, who’s also vegan,
‘Oh, Saj is great, he’s eating hardly any meat these days.’
And then we went out for Chinese and he ordered pork dumplings
and I just didn’t make eye contact with my mum.
Emily: And, Rebecca, when you watched Saj eat the pork, how did that feel?
Rebecca: I guess it’s a mix of annoyance,
’cause I really wish he didn’t eat it, and sadness,
’cause I thought that you weren’t eating pork much any more and I, like, love pigs.
Emily: Now, apparently, they didn’t row about it on the way home.
For these two, it’s love before lamb chops, tenderness before teriyaki.
But, if Rebecca had been a vegan when they first met,
would this relationship have ever got off the ground?
Rebecca: I think my militance would get on your nerves
and your meat eating would be intolerable for me.